<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Carson Farmer</title><link href="http://www.carsonfarmer.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.carsonfarmer.com/feeds/big-data.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.carsonfarmer.com/</id><updated>2014-10-28T14:33:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>What Do We Do With All This Big Data?</title><link href="http://www.carsonfarmer.com/2014/10/what-to-do-with-all-this-data/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-28T14:33:00-04:00</updated><author><name>cfarmer</name></author><id>tag:www.carsonfarmer.com,2014-10-28:2014/10/what-to-do-with-all-this-data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting and thought-provoking &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TED&lt;/span&gt; Talk by &lt;a href="http://susanetlinger.wordpress.com"&gt;Susan Etlinger&lt;/a&gt; about how important it is to encourage &amp;#8216;critical thinking&amp;#8217; when it comes to Big Data. Here, the idea is not let the &amp;#8216;data speak for themselves&amp;#8217; but rather tell an engaging and intelligent story &amp;#8216;with data&amp;#8217;. Basically, we need to move &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; counting things in order to really understand&amp;nbsp;anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;CENTER&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://embed-ssl.ted.com/talks/susan_etlinger_what_do_we_do_with_all_this_big_data.html" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/CENTER&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with pretty much everything Susan says, and her use of a very personal example really deepens the impact of her talk. I really liked her focus on the need for &amp;#8216;deepening our critical thinking skills&amp;#8217;, and I think this is something we need to ensure we are passing on to our students as well. Putting less focus on what the &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; say, and more focus on what we can learn &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the data is something we should be teaching more at the undergraduate, graduate, and even high-school levels. I think the statistics literature and curriculum(s), while often slow to respond to modern teaching methods, are much better at this perspective than their machine learning counterparts; but this need not be the case, and I hope as we continue to generate, collect, store, and analyze more and more data, we keep in mind the &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2013/04/with-big-data-context-is-a-big-issue/"&gt;need for context&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Video"></category><category term="Internet"></category><category term="Big Data"></category></entry></feed>