<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Carson Farmer</title><link href="http://carsonfarmer.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://carsonfarmer.com/feeds/guest-speaker.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://carsonfarmer.com/</id><updated>2013-05-28T18:29:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Tim Stojanovic Guest Lecture</title><link href="http://carsonfarmer.com/2013/05/guest-speaker-june-2013/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-28T18:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>cfarmer</name></author><id>tag:carsonfarmer.com,2013-05-28:2013/05/guest-speaker-june-2013/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/gsd/people/tas21/"&gt;Dr. Tim Stojanovic&lt;/a&gt; will be coming to the &lt;a href="http://www.geo.hunter.cuny.edu/"&gt;Department of Geography 
at Hunter College&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CUNY&lt;/span&gt; next week to give a talk entitled: &amp;#8220;Analysing 
Change in the Human Development of the World’s Oceans&amp;#8221;. The talk will be held 
on &lt;strong&gt;June 5th, 2013&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;3:00 p.m.&lt;/strong&gt; in the Hunter North building, room 1004.
The talk is hosted by the Department of Geography, and the poster is &lt;a href="http://carsonfarmer.com/uploads/stojanovic_human_dev_oceans.pdf"&gt;available 
here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://carsonfarmer.com/images/global-oceans.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="right" src="http://carsonfarmer.com/images/global-oceans-400x265.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The World’s oceans are a frontline for sustainability, given the expansion of 
human activity in coasts and seas, changes brought about by human forcing 
factors, and changes in the global ocean-atmosphere system.  Making an 
assessment of the extent and significance of change is a challenge for science, 
given the relative paucity of data and the multiple variables involved.  This 
paper reports on a study to empirically tests notions of &amp;#8216;industrialisation&amp;#8217; and 
&amp;#8216;colonisation&amp;#8217; in the oceans for the first time. The approach draws on a key 
global spatial dataset developed by Halpern et al (2008). The methods include 
the combined use of Raster and R to overcome methodological challenges in 
analysing large spatial datasets which map the footprint of human activity in 
the world&amp;#8217;s oceans. The findings show that human activity in the oceans has 
increased by multiple factors in the most recent long term wave of economic 
development and show distinct spatial patterns of development.  Further 
refinement of this assessment is required and is likely to be driven by a 
recently established &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UN&lt;/span&gt; Global Assessment of the State of the Marine&amp;nbsp;Environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Speaker&amp;nbsp;bio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/gsd/people/tas21/"&gt;&lt;img alt="image2" class="left" src="http://carsonfarmer.com/images/stojanovic.jpg" title="Dr. Tim Stojanovic, Lecturer in Geography &amp;amp; Sustainable Development, Department of Geography &amp;amp; Sustainable Development,  Scottish Oceans Institute, Sustainability Institute,  University of St Andrews, UK" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Tim Stojanovic is a Lecturer (i.e. Associate Professor) in Geography and 
Sustainable Development at the University of St Andrews, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;. He has a PhD and 
BSc in Marine Geography from Cardiff University, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;.  Dr Stojanovic’s research 
interests relate to the sustainability of oceans and coasts, including work 
with interdisciplinary research teams in issues such as climate adaptation and 
ecosystem services, and social science research on effective&amp;nbsp;governance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to learn more about the talk, the venue, or Dr Stojanovic&amp;#8217;s 
work, please &lt;a href="http://carsonfarmer.com/contact/"&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt; for further&amp;nbsp;details.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Human Impacts"></category><category term="Policy"></category><category term="Research"></category><category term="Sustainability"></category><category term="Oceans"></category></entry></feed>