<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Carson Farmer</title><link href="www.carsonfarmer.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="www.carsonfarmer.com/feeds/visualisation.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>www.carsonfarmer.com/</id><updated>2012-08-10T14:07:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>cartogram updates</title><link href="www.carsonfarmer.com/2012/08/cartogram-updates/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-08-10T14:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>cfarmer</name></author><id>tag:www.carsonfarmer.com,2012-08-10:2012/08/cartogram-updates/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seems my &lt;a href="examples/olympic_countries/"&gt;Olympic medals cartogram&lt;/a&gt; is getting a bit more attention
(&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/datablog/interactive/2012/aug/10/olympics-medals-visualised"&gt;Guardian data blog&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/olympics/olympic_infographics_and_data/9467077/London-2012-Olympics-interactive-world-medal-map-by-population-GDP-and-geographical-size.html"&gt;Telegraph data and graphics blog&lt;/a&gt;), so
I&amp;#8217;ve updated a few things and wanted to highlight/explain them a bit&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="examples/olympic_countries/"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://www.carsonfarmer.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/grenada.png" title="grenada" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, you can now explore the medal data together with
population &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt; as well as without any warping to get a feel for
how much things change. Secondly, in order to be able to display the map
in a way that is familiar to most people (i.e., landscape style), I had
to take a few liberties in terms of representation. For instance, the
&amp;#8216;projection&amp;#8217; used is not area preserving (in fact, it is just the
geographical coordinates), so some countries appear larger (smaller)
than they should, even with the warping. We all make compromises though
right? Third, because I wasn&amp;#8217;t happy with adding artificial medal counts
to make my algorithm happy, I decided to create a more &amp;#8216;realistic&amp;#8217;
graphic, so this time around, countries with zero medals have zero area
(i.e. are removed). Related to this, because Grenada only has about
110,821 people, its &lt;a href="http://www.medalspercapita.com/"&gt;per capita medal ranking&lt;/a&gt; is off the charts (note
that I&amp;#8217;m not using the the &lt;a href="http://www.medalspercapita.com/"&gt;http://www.medalspercapita.com/&lt;/a&gt; figures for the graphic)! This, coupled with its tiny
size, means that my cartogram algorithm emphasises Grenada at the
expense of all the other countries, making the graphic pretty boring
unless you live in Grenada. As a result, I&amp;#8217;ve excluded all countries
with less than two medals in total (I know, I&amp;#8217;m sorry, but it had to be
done). Having said that, if you click to view the &amp;#8216;normal&amp;#8217; map, then all
countries are added back, and you get medal counts for all of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Cartogram"></category><category term="Olympics"></category><category term="Update"></category><category term="Visualisation"></category><category term="Update"></category></entry><entry><title>Olympic cartogram</title><link href="www.carsonfarmer.com/2012/08/olympic-cartogram/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-08-02T12:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>cfarmer</name></author><id>tag:www.carsonfarmer.com,2012-08-02:2012/08/olympic-cartogram/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The London 2012 Summer Olympics have generated quite a bit of buzz in
terms of visualisations and interesting data analysis. In fact, news
sites here in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; are doing all sorts of cools things with Olympic
data, and &lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/"&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; has an &lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/series/london-2012-olympics-data"&gt;entire series&lt;/a&gt; devoted to Olympic
data. A colleague of mine also pointed out a &lt;a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/olympics/9436640/London-2012-Olympics-dynamic-world-medal-map.html"&gt;cool graphic&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/"&gt;The
Telegraph&lt;/a&gt; website, which is essentially a live cartogram of Olympic
medal counts. The cartogram is basically a spatial bubble plot, with the
size of the bubbles representing the number of medals obtained by each
country. The location of each bubbled is based on the corresponding
country&amp;#8217;s approximate geographic location. The graphic is pretty
effective, and it certainly tells a clear&amp;nbsp;story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m a big fan of these types of abstract &lt;a href="http://www.unicef.org/sowc2012/urbanmap/"&gt;representations of space&lt;/a&gt;,
so I thought The Telegraph&amp;#8217;s graphic was pretty fun. Having said that,
I&amp;#8217;m always a sucker for a more &amp;#8216;traditional&amp;#8217; rubber-sheet cartogram,
which is generally less abstract than a bubble plot, but can sometimes
lead to &lt;a href="http://www.worldmapper.org/"&gt;dramatic results&lt;/a&gt;. Since I felt like the only person on the
internet without their own Olympics visualisation, I decided to throw
together a cartogram to visualise Olympic medal achievements. Drawing
inspiration from The Telegraph graphic, I created a rubber-sheet
cartogram based on an &lt;a href="http://lambert.nico.free.fr/tp/biblio/Dougeniketal1985.pdf"&gt;iterative warping method&lt;/a&gt;. The &amp;#8216;live&amp;#8217; version
of the cartogram is &lt;a href="examples/olympic_countries/"&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt; (or by clicking on the image
below). [&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPDATE&lt;/span&gt;] If you&amp;#8217;d like to include the map on a web page, you can
now do that by including this in your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;source:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;iframe&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;http://www.carsonfarmer.com/examples/olympic_countries_map.html&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;width=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;1230&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;height=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;545\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="examples/olympic_countries/"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="www.carsonfarmer.com/static/images/olympic_carto.png" title="Olympic cartogram" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cartgram is interactive, and was created using &lt;a href="http://www.python.org/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/esnme/ultrajson"&gt;ujson&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://toblerity.github.com/shapely/manual.html"&gt;shapely&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt;. If I get a
chance, I&amp;#8217;ll try to post the code at some stage. In the mean time, here
is a bit more info about the&amp;nbsp;graphic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of each country is based on the total number of medals that
they have achieved, weighted by the type of medal (gold, silver,
bronze). For example, a country with one gold medal should be
approximately the same size as a country with three bronze medals.
Because the algorithm attempts to maintain the topological relationships
between countries, this relationship might not be perfect, but the
general trend is clear: the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; and China and cleaning up! [&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPDATE&lt;/span&gt;] I&amp;#8217;ve
also added relative per capita medal counts and counts by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt;, which
shrinks China down significantly&amp;#8230; now who&amp;#8217;s winning&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8216;big&amp;#8217;?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t have full access to the server that this website is running on,
&lt;strike&gt;so I couldn&amp;#8217;t get things set up with regular updates,&lt;/strike&gt; however, the
entire process is now automated, so &lt;strike&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll try to have the code run at
fairly regular intervals so that the results are relatively up-to-date&lt;/strike&gt;
I now have the maps updating every hour. In any case, have a play around
and let me know what you think, and if you know of any other cool
Olympics graphics or cool applications of cartograms, please let me know
in the&amp;nbsp;comments!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Cartogram"></category><category term="Olympics"></category><category term="Visualisation"></category></entry><entry><title>Visualising data with FatFonts</title><link href="www.carsonfarmer.com/2012/05/visualising-data-with-fatfonts/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-05-26T20:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>cfarmer</name></author><id>tag:www.carsonfarmer.com,2012-05-26:2012/05/visualising-data-with-fatfonts/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently posted an &lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/geoinformatics/visualising-with-fatfonts/"&gt;article on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CGI&lt;/span&gt; blog&lt;/a&gt; about some
visualisations that I produced with researchers from [St Andrews&amp;#8217;
Computer Human Interaction Research Group (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SACHI&lt;/span&gt;)][] using &lt;a href="http://fatfonts.org/"&gt;FatFonts&lt;/a&gt;,
a tpographic visualisation technique developed by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SACHI&lt;/span&gt; co-founder
&lt;a href="http://nacenta.com/about/"&gt;Miguel Nacenta&lt;/a&gt; and colleagues (&lt;a href="http://www.utahinrichs.de/"&gt;Uta Hinrichs&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~sheelagh/wiki/pmwiki.php"&gt;Sheelagh
Carpendale&lt;/a&gt;).
The initial visualisations are now on-line, and feature flow matrices for 
&lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/geoinformatics/examples/fatfonts/uk-migration/"&gt;English internal migration&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/geoinformatics/examples/fatfonts/irish-commuting/"&gt;commuting between Irish local labour markets&lt;/a&gt;. We
have also produced several inforgraphics based on global oceans data
that &lt;a href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/gsd/people/tas21/"&gt;Dr Timothy Stojanovic&lt;/a&gt; and I are working with as part of
Tim&amp;#8217;s work linking off-shore cumulative human impacts to
on-shore terrestrial urbanization (more on these graphics soon). I&amp;#8217;m
still experimenting with FatFonts at this stage, but so far, I&amp;#8217;m quite
pleased with the results, and find that they offer a nice way to add
beauty to my potentially boring data!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="www.carsonfarmer.com/static/images/fat_fonts.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="www.carsonfarmer.com/static/images/fat_fonts-300x122.png" title="Subset of FatFont image" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carson&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Research"></category><category term="FatFonts"></category><category term="News"></category><category term="Feature"></category></entry><entry><title>Research dissemination and interactive visuals</title><link href="www.carsonfarmer.com/2012/04/research-dissemination-and-interactive-visuals/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-04-10T22:12:00-04:00</updated><author><name>cfarmer</name></author><id>tag:www.carsonfarmer.com,2012-04-10:2012/04/research-dissemination-and-interactive-visuals/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my goals for this year is to spend more time and effort
developing effective visualisations for my various research projects, in
an effort to make my research more accessible to others. This is one
thing that I think many academics are particularly bad at: letting
others know what they are up to, and why it might be something worth
looking at. In order to avoid this pitfall, I plan to focus on producing
interactive, web-based visuals suitable for a more general audience &lt;em&gt;in
addition&lt;/em&gt; to more traditional forms of research dissemination such as
journals and conference papers. It is my hope that by doing this, I will
be making my research more readily available to those who might actually
be able to use it, and maybe even create some compelling visualisations
in the process. While I&amp;#8217;m not quite ready to start creating full-blown
interactive websites yet, I thought it might be a good idea to start
with something small to get the ball rolling; so I put together an
&lt;a href="/examples/visitors/"&gt;upgraded version&lt;/a&gt; of my &lt;a href="www.carsonfarmer.com/2012/03/because-its-fun-to-map-stuff/"&gt;previous map&lt;/a&gt; of visitors to www.carsonfarmer.com.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the excellent &lt;a href="http://mbostock.github.com/d3/"&gt;D3 JavaScript library&lt;/a&gt; to re-create the visitor
map, this time providing some basic interaction with the data. Most of
the functionality is based on &lt;a href="http://mbostock.github.com/d3/ex/"&gt;examples&lt;/a&gt; from the D3 website, and at
this point, the map is really more of a learning tool than anything. As
in my previous static map, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt; addresses were geocoded using the
&lt;a href="http://www.datasciencetoolkit.org/"&gt;Data Science Toolkit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; via the &lt;a href="https://github.com/rtelmore/RDSTK"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RDSTK&lt;/span&gt; R package&lt;/a&gt;, and all data
processing and manipulation was done using R. Additionally, the colour
scheme functionality comes from &lt;a href="http://mbostock.github.com/d3/talk/20111018/#25"&gt;slide 25&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://mbostock.github.com/d3/talk/20111018/#0"&gt;this presentation&lt;/a&gt;,
and uses the sequential colour palettes from &lt;a href="http://colorbrewer2.org/"&gt;colorbrewer.org&lt;/a&gt;. There
are still a few kinks to work out (like how to get the &lt;code&gt;onmouseout&lt;/code&gt; event
to work properly in Internet Explorer), and tonnes of additional
features and functions could be added, so comments and suggestions are
welcome. Having said that, I think the new version looks quite nice, and
will likely form the basis for more complex visuals as I become more
familiar with Javascipt and various other web-development&amp;nbsp;tools.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="D3"></category><category term="Interactive"></category><category term="Javascript"></category><category term="Online Maps"></category><category term="Visualisation"></category><category term="Free open-source software (FOSS)"></category><category term="Opinion"></category></entry></feed>